part of this video is sponsored by
LastPass more about LastPass at the end
of the show this is a video about
research into slowing the rate of Aging
and extending the human lifespan so
before I film this I wanted to know what
do you guys generally think about such
research and I made a Twitter poll where
I found that the majority of people were
supportive and thought there should be
more of it but there were some important
concerns and I want to address those
here at the beginning I mean the most
significant concern was if we're looking
to extend human lifespan does that just
mean we'll have more sick years where
we'll be in bed with Alzheimer's nobody
wants that and that was clear to me but
the professor that I was interviewing
for this video professor David Sinclair
points out that as you get older the
risk of Horrible diseases things like
diabetes and cancer and arthritis all
those sorts of things it increases
exponentially and so if this research is
successful the whole point of it will be
to forestall those sorts of diseases I
mean if you really are tackling aging
then you should also see that those
age-related diseases do not set in so
quickly
so the point of slowing aging and
extending human lifespan is to extend
the healthy lifespan also called the
health span the other concerns I saw
were that people were saying well this
could be used only for the wealthy and
increase inequality or it could increase
the population of the earth causing you
know garbage more co2 you know where the
resources to feed all these people I
think these are valid concerns but
they're not part of the scope of this
video so if you want to discuss them in
the comments feel free but the point of
this video is to address can we slow
aging in humans can we extend the
lifespan and the health span and what
does that look like how do we do it okay
so for this video I traveled up to the
bodega Marine Lab which is north of San
Francisco and there I got to see some
moon jellyfish now it's fascinating
about these moon jellyfishes some people
consider them and more
how can that be so all these jellyfish
have this complex life cycle where they
start off as a polyp which is basically
like a small sea anemone and then
they'll go through a metamorphosis and
become a Medusa and the Medusa stage is
what we generally think of when we think
about a jellyfish and in most of these
species the polyps are generally able to
asexually reproduce and they can
regenerate if tissue is cut off of them
or if they're damaged and they don't
have any clear evidence of senescence
which is the term for biological aging
so they appear to have some degree of
immortality no one had reported their
ability to do this until I think this
was 2015 so do moon jellyfish hold the
key to slowing aging and extending our
lifespan could they help us live forever
before I got into making this video I
would have put this sort of research in
the same category as downloading your
brain your consciousness into a computer
like I can see how maybe that would work
but I don't think we're anywhere near
that because we don't even understand
how the brain works or how memories are
stored so that seems like serious
science fiction so I would have put say
extending the human lifespan to 120 150
and Beyond in the same category but
after reading professor Sinclair's book
and doing an interview with him I think
it seems much more possible and in fact
plausible that will make some progress
over controlling Aging in our lifetimes
now if you want to slow aging the first
question you need to answer is why do we
age in the first place I mean what
really is aging I've made a video in the
past about telomeres these are the end
caps on your chromosomes and every time
a cell divides the telomere gets a bit
shorter so it was thought that these
telomeres are kind of like the tips of
your shoelaces and they prevent the
chromosome from fraying but there are
other signs in older bodies that you
have old cells there are an accumulation
of things they're called senescent cells
they're essentially these zombie-like
stels that just go on living in your
body and inflaming the cells around them
there's poor intercellular communication
there's mitochondrial dysfunction those
are the powerhouses of the cell there
are these eight or nine different
features of older cells and they are the
hallmarks of aging but the question is
are they the cause of aging or are they
kind of the result of a deeper root
cause in the middle of the last century
the hypothesis was that it was damaged
to our DNA mutations to our DNA that
happened of the course of our lives that
led us to be older but evidence since
then has suggested that that is not
really the case when you can take an
adult cell and you can clone it into a
new organism and that organism appears
to live about as long as non cloned
organisms of the same species
now the first shaped Dolly the sheep had
a short lifespan
she died early but cloned animals you
can now clone a monkey you can clone
dogs in fact barbra streisand the
actress she cloned her dogs and they're
expected to live a normal lifespan so in
that way it seems like all the
information is still there in the DNA so
if we're not losing information in our
DNA then what is the reason for aging
well professor Sinclair suspects that
it's a loss of information but not the
information in our DNA in our genome no
professor Sinclair suspects that the
loss of information is in our EPI genome
so what is the epigenome every cell in
your body has the same DNA but different
cell types have different epigenomes
they have different ways of packaging
that DNA coiling up you know a lot of it
so that it's not red and leaving some
parts of the DNA spooled out so it's
easier to transcribe and turn into
proteins and run that cell so the
epigenome is responsible for turning on
or turning off different parts of the
DNA the way it does that is with
proteins called histones that
essentially the DNA is wrapped on
and also things like methylation so
there's these chemical signaling markers
which are placed on the DNA in certain
positions so the idea is when your body
is first forming the epigenome is what
tells your cells what type of cell to be
but as you get older
professor Sinclair's hypothesis is that
we are losing information in the
epigenome and that's important because
if a skin cell needs to remain a skin
cell that's the epigenome
and if you don't have the epigenome the
skin cell will forget what type of cell
it is and it might turn into a brain
cell which may not be that bad but if
your brain turns into a skin cell you've
got a problem and I think that's largely
what aging is I've gotta say like
there's some weird like hair patches
like on my shoulder that have happened
as I've gotten older is that a cell like
doing the wrong thing are those meant to
be skin cells so they screwing up or is
this just some I don't know no no weird
stuff happens when you get older right
you start to get hair growing where it
shouldn't ears nose back that's cells
losing their identity cells go I can't
remember what I'm supposed to do I'm not
reading the right genes anymore so the
key to this sort of breakdown of the
epigenome is DNA damage yeah so when you
go out in the Sun and not like today but
on a day where there's a lot of Sun
you'll break your chromosomes and in the
effort that the cells go to to stick the
chromosome back together note the DNA
isn't just flailing around it's actually
bundled up the cell has to unwrap it
recruit proteins to help join it
together and then they have to go back
and reset the structures and that
resetting of the epigenome happens about
99% that 1% is the aging process
so overtime histones are not returned to
the right places and DNA methylation is
added in places where it shouldn't be we
can read that methylation pattern and I
could tell you how old you are exactly
and when you're even gonna die how could
you tell that well the it's a clock we
call it the Horvath clock named after my
good friend Steve Horvath and so these
little chemicals that accumulate on the
DNA like plaque on the teeth we can read
that and the more you have the older you
are biologically so you might only be 40
you're younger than 40 of course you you
know I'm 50 now but I might be
biologically 60 actually I was and I
changed my life and then the test said I
was biologically 31 I mean one of the
things I found really interesting was
you found a way to make mice age faster
so how'd you do that
well the clock of aging is due to the
loss of the information in the cell and
one way to accelerate that is to go
break a chromosome instead of going in
the Sun we engineered a mouse where we
could break its chromosomes not enough
to cause mutations the cells put the DNA
back together so we didn't lose any
genetic information but if we're right
about the epigenetic information theory
of aging those mice should get old and
that's exactly what happened that's gray
it's got a hunchback it's got dementia
all its organs look old but the real
test was what if we measured that DNA
clock the what we call the DNA
methylation clock and we measured it and
those mice were actually 50% older than
mice that we didn't treat so that isn't
just a mouse that looks old
that Mouse literally is older what's
interesting about this hypothesis is
that if it's true if the noise
accumulating the epigenome is really
what's causing aging well then there are
steps we can take right now to slow the
rate of Aging in our bodies by trying to
better maintain our epigenomes so how do
we do that there's this theory that
billions of years ago early bacteria
took an important evolutionary step they
actually developed two different modes
of living when times were good
they used their energy to grow and
reproduce but when conditions were tough
they used their energy to protect and
repair their cells they evolved what
professor Sinclair calls longevity genes
these genes triggered by adversity
create enzymes which among other things
maintain the epigenome and today those
same longevity genes can be found in
bacteria and us we have these or metic
response genes or longevity genes that
are in all of our cells and they sense
when we've run a lot we've lost our
breath or we're hungry we were a little
bit hot but a little bit cold that these
genes are turning on our general
defenses against aging so what is that
so parts of our cells fall apart they
can put them back together
proteins miss fold they can get rid of
them or put them back together the ends
of the chromosomes get shorter they can
lengthen them a lot of processes that go
on but one of the most important I think
is maintaining the information the
epigenetic information in a cell so that
our cells don't forget what to do
there are three types of longevity gene
they're the ones we work on called
sirtuins and they control the
information in the cell in fact sir in
the sirtuin stands for silent
information regulator number two there
are other ones the other group is called
EMP kinase or AMPK this group of genes
senses how much energy were we're taking
in for mostly in the form of sugar and
then the third group is called mTOR and
these genes control and respond to how
much amino acids were taking in so if
you eat a giant steak you've got a lot
of amino acids coming into your body
that'll actually prevent mTOR from
hunkering down and keeping you being
longer lived so the mouse experiments
actually bear this out the best way to
make a mouse live longer is to reduce
the amount of time it eats so periodic
fasting intermittent fasting to keep it
a little bit cool and to restrict its
amino acids that's the recipe for long
life for a mouse and it's true for
monkeys as well they've been calorie
restricted studies where these monkeys
for 15 years didn't eat as much food as
the ones that gorged themselves whenever
they wanted and they were protected
they didn't just age slower they didn't
get as much died
and heart disease they're actually fit
and healthy when the control group
eating whatever they wanted aged and
became sick quicker when some people
think about eating less like calorie
restriction as a way to extend their
life that doesn't seem like a very
pleasant way to extend life I mean to be
hungry for longer so are there other
ways to you know mimic that effect or to
simulate that there are these molecules
that turn on the sirtuin pathway and
trick the body and so for example in the
lab if I give some of our mice a
molecule called nmn which raises the
level of a chemical called nad you get
hyperactive defenses in the body and
what did you see in these you know
senescent mice that you gave in a mentor
well we had a bit of an incident these
mice that we gave nmn to ran 50% further
but actually some of them ran so far
that the Machine the little treadmill
stopped working and we had to reprogram
the software because this program had
never seen a mouse that ran more than
three kilometres three kilometers for a
mouse for an old Mouse they outran the
young mice and that's like an
ultramarathon for us that would be
probably like taking a 70 year old and
making them run faster than a 20 year
old further yes so these are ultra
marathoners and if we did that to humans
imagine you could have 90 year olds
winning Olympic medals so to sum up
there are six things that you can do
right now to slow the rate of your aging
starting with zero avoid DNA damage wear
sunscreen avoid x-rays and all that sort
of stuff
number one eat less caloric restriction
number two eat less protein because your
body has ways of detecting how much of
that you're taking in number three do
some exercise high-intensity interval
training get your heart rate up to 85%
make your body feel like you're running
from a lion or something number four be
uncomfortably cold or number five be
uncomfortably hot all of these things
will trigger your body's longevity genes
into maintaining your epigenome going in
to repair and protect mode rather
then grow and reproduce if you think
about those things those are generally
all the things that we don't do
but what if slowing aging isn't enough
for you well this is where my interview
with professor Sinclair took an
interesting turn because he's actually
done some research on reversing aging so
how would you do that well effectively
you would need to take the epigenome and
reset it back to an earlier time but how
is that possible back in 2012 a
scientist named Yamanaka received the
Nobel Prize for discovering four factors
which when applied in a gene therapy to
an adult cell would reset the whole
epigenome back to how that cell was when
it was an embryo so it is what is called
a pluripotent stem cell now you wouldn't
want to apply that to your entire body
because well then you would turn into a
giant tumor because your cells wouldn't
know how to differentiate but it does
suggest that there are ways of resetting
your epigenome and they could be the key
to reversing aging the big breakthrough
that we just had in my lab finally you
know about a year or so ago was to
reprogram the eye of a mouse and the eye
we chose the eye because that's a very
hard thing to fix right if you go blind
when you're older we think that's a
one-way thing you're never going to
recover your vision but we decided let's
try it anyway let's let's go for broke
so we put a gene therapy in the eye of
old mice turn their retinas to be young
again reversed Aging in their retinas
so those one-year old mice went back to
about two months and guess what those
mice could see again just like they were
young and again how do you reset one of
these eye cells without resetting it to
just a stem cell well we have to be very
careful not to reset these cells to be
basically a stem cell otherwise we
wouldn't have mice they can see we'd
have mice with a giant tumor in the back
of their eyes so what we do is a couple
of things we didn't use all of the for
reprogramming factors that won the Nobel
Prize we use just three we leave off one
called Mik which causes cancer and those
three seem to be just the right recipe
for taking the age of
the I backwoods but not too far then the
second thing we do is we turn it off we
can actually turn this system on when we
want and off again so that we don't take
them too far back in age can you do that
with any cell we think we can do this in
any tissue where we've now given it to
the whole mouse and those mice are fine
no evidence of cancer they seem to be
really quite healthy so the big question
is can you take a mouse way back the
whole body and be totally young in maybe
back from two years back to two months
and that's what we're doing right now
that's pretty exciting it's freakishly
exciting actually I thought we just slow
down aging now we're talking about an
aging reset you know what we've only
reset the age of the eye once how many
times can we do this maybe it's twice
maybe it's a hundred times so professor
Sinclair claims that his gene therapy
reversed Aging in the mouse's eye and
allowed it to see again but applying a
gene therapy to every one of your
trillion cells is pretty impossible so
in order for this to actually work and
reset an entire body you would need
another way and this is where the
jellyfish come in because moon jellyfish
any cell in an adult jellyfish can
actually be reset into an earlier stage
of its life cycle it can become a polyp
again so it seems like the jellyfish are
actually capable of activating something
like the Yamanaka factors and resetting
their epigenomes to an earlier time in
their lives if we're able to figure out
how they do that well then maybe we
could do the same with our own cells we
do have the ability to reset our
epigenomes but that is typically only
used when we're in the embryonic stage
when we need to maintain all our cells
as stem cells as we age most mammals
including humans we lose stem cells over
time and the stem cells we do have
become more and more restricted over
time into the types of cells they can
make so if we can understand how the
moon jellyfish can take presumably many
different kinds of cells
and reverse-engineer them into the cells
that needs during regeneration that
might give us an idea how to do it in
ourselves as well so I still think were
a fair ways off from reversing aging in
the entire human body but what I found
interesting from talking to professor
Sinclair was that there's at least a
roadmap at least a path ahead where you
can see that it could be possible to
slow and even reverse aging
hey this part of the video is sponsored
by LastPass so let's talk about one
thing you can do right now to improve
your life just go to LastPass calm and
start a free account and enjoy free
cross-device sync think about how
spending just a few moments right now
could save you hours or even days over
the course of your life and that's
because you will never again get locked
out of an account you'll never have to
reset a password you'll no longer have
to burden your brain with remembering
passwords or end up having to write them
down and it will make your passwords
more secure because LastPass Auto
generates strong passwords for you I
love how it auto fills usernames and
passwords on websites and it works just
as well on iOS or Android apps and
mobile sites just think about how much
hassle in time this will save you if you
end up living to like a hundred or a
hundred and twenty I mean how many
accounts and passwords will you even
have by then and if you want extra
features like advanced multi-factor
authentication you can upgrade to
LastPass premium so put your passwords
on autopilot right now with LastPass
click on the link below to find out more
and thanks to LastPass for sponsoring
this part of the video